A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, European and International Affairs Program (EIA), Office Files of Peter Ruof FA1514
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, European and International Affairs Program (EIA), Office Files of Peter Ruof
1973-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ruof, Peter
Ford Foundation
FA1514
2.47 Cubic Feet 6 LTR and 1 Half-LTR size Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the staff subject files of Peter Ruof who worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's European and International Affairs Program (EIA) between 1973 and 1981 and then as an international consultant for the Foundation's International Affairs Program (IAP) for a brief period after that. The EIA was situated within the Foundation's International Division. Materials in the collection relate how it was replaced by the IAP in the early 1980s. Ruof's records are comprised of chronological files that were created between 1973 and 1978 and between 1981 and 1982. Files originating from the period between November 1978 and September 1981 are missing from the collection.
Chronological files in the collection are mainly comprised of correspondence, memos, papers, and meeting notes. They document the EIA's grant giving activities for studies, initiatives, and fellowships related to Western and Southern Europe. Prominent subjects upon which these different projects were focused include international economics, migrant labor, Eurocommunism, women's issues, international relations, foundations in Europe, and European policy studies
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers' papers were transferred to, and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:022.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series. That series is comprised of chronological files. Documents within those files are arranged in reverse chronological order, so the most recent material is at the front of the files.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Chronological files, 1973-1982
Biographical / Historical
Peter Ruof worked as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's European and International Affairs Program (EIA) between 1973 and 1981. Before joining the Foundation's International Division, he had positions at the Commission of the European Union, the International Monetary Fund, and the World Bank.
After he left his post as Program Officer, he worked as an international consultant for the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program (IAP) in the early 1980s. In 1995, he founded Blackwood Capital Group.
Other Finding Aids
Finding aids concerning the office files of other Ford Foundation staff members in the European and International Affairs Program include:
FA1509 Ford Foundation records, International Division, European and International Affairs Program (EIA), Office Files of Ruth D. Carter
Ford Foundation; Europe; Europe, Western; Europe, Southern; Germany; Migrant labor; Communism -- Europe; International economic relations; International relations
- Chronological files, 1973-1982; 1; 2.47 Cubic Feet 6 LTR and 1 Half-LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the chronological files of Peter Ruof. Files originating from between 1973 and 1978 document Ruof's time as a Program Officer in the Ford Foundation's European and International Affairs Program (EIA). They are comprised of memos and correspondence that Ruof addressed to grantees, potential grantees, consultants, Foundation staff members, and other associated professionals. In these documents, Ruof discusses such items as: Grant proposal acceptances, rejections, and reviews; grant extensions, closeouts, and evaluations; business travel to different European countries and other destinations; and meetings regarding Foundation supported projects. Chronological files created between November 1978 and September 1981 are missing from the series.
  The last few files in the series originate from between October 1981 and October 1982. They concern Ruof's departure from the Ford Foundation, the restructuring of the EIA into the International Affairs Program (IAP), and Ruof's time working as an international consultant for the IAP.
  Grants and other projects that Ruof oversaw and supported during his time as Program Officer and international consultant include the Future of the International Economic Order research competition (IEO), initiatives aimed at improving relations between the United States and different European nations such as Germany, France, and Italy, the development of a Ford Foundation Southern European Fellowship Program, the Foundation's continued support of the Trilateral Commission, a conference to discuss the international commodities market, a conference between U.S. and European foundations, support of Cynthia Epstein and other academics studying issues related to women in Europe, research about communism in Southern Europe, and the establishment of an independent European policy studies institute.
  - Chronological file, 1973-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Chronological file, 1973 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological file, 1973 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological file, 1973 December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological file, 1974 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological file, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological file, 1974 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological file, 1974 April (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chronological file, 1974 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chronological file, 1974 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chronological file, 1974 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chronological file, 1974 August (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chronological file, 1974 September (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chronological file, 1974 October (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chronological file, 1974 November (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chronological file, 1974 December (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chronological file, 1975 January (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Chronological file, 1975 February (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chronological file, 1975 March (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Chronological file, 1975 April (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Chronological file, 1975 May (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Chronological file, 1975 June (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chronological file, 1975 July (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Chronological file, 1975 August (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Chronological file, 1975 September (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Chronological file, 1975 October (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Chronological file, 1975 November (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Chronological file, 1975 December (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Chronological file, 1976 January (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Chronological file, 1976 February (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Chronological file, 1976 March (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Chronological file, 1976 April (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Chronological file, 1976 May (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Chronological file, 1976 June (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Chronological file, 1976 July (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chronological file, 1976 August (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Chronological file, 1976 September (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Chronological file, 1976 October (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Chronological file, 1976 November (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Chronological file, 1976 December (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Chronological file, 1977 January (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Chronological file, 1977 February (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Chronological file, 1977 March (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Chronological file, 1977 April (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Chronological file, 1977 May (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Chronological file, 1977 June (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Chronological file, 1977 July (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Chronological file, 1977 August (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Chronological file, 1977 September (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Chronological file, 1977 October (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Chronological file, 1977 November (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Chronological file, 1977 December (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Chronological file, 1978 January (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Chronological file, 1978 February (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Chronological file, 1978 March (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Chronological file, 1978 April (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Chronological file, 1978 May (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Chronological file, 1978 June (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Chronological file, 1978 July (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Chronological file, 1978 August (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Chronological file, 1978 September (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Chronological file, 1978 October (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Chronological file, 1981 October (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Chronological file, 1981 November (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Chronological file, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Chronological file, 1982 March (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Chronological file, 1982 April-October (Box 7, Folder 68)